Preliminary Guide to the Doolittle Collection of Japanese Drama
Yale University Arts Library
The Doolittle Collection of Japanese Drama
1897-1974
DRA 11
Yale University Arts Library
4.17
(10 boxes)
The collection contains numerous designs of unknown origin depicting scenes from the traditional Japanese stage. The scenes displayed are derived from Noh (or Nō) dramas, a performance tradition which draws on Buddhist scripture and Japanese mythology and combines music, dance, and poetry in a highly formalized staging.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Doolittle Collection of Japanese Drama was housed in the former Drama Library until its transfer to the Robert B. Haas Family Arts Library in 2008.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
The collection contains numerous designs of unknown origin depicting scenes from the traditional Japanese stage. The scenes displayed are derived from Noh (or Nō) dramas, a performance tradition which draws on Buddhist scripture and Japanese mythology and combines music, dance, and poetry in a highly formalized staging.
Arrangement
Box listing only.
Nō -- Japan -- Pictorial works; Nō; Printouts; Denton, Mary Florence, 1857?-1947
- Box listing
  - 47 colored prints of theatrical scenes from Nō̄̄ plays; labeled #1-12; #12c.2-46; #67-70; #355, undated (Box 1)
  - 20 colored prints with handwritten notes; labeled #47-66, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - 1 black and white photograph of figure in Nō costume; labeled #239, undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - 25 handwritten notes to accompany each print pair; labeled #84-109, undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - "No Sugata (Figure of Nō dance)" folder containing photo, Japanese text, colored drawings, and prints., undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - 1 unbound book, No-Dance Pictures, containing 124 colored prints in 3 parts with corresponding handwritten notes by Kogyo; labeled #110-195, 1897-1898 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - 1 figure painting on canvas panel; labeled #228, undated; 9 inches x 12 inches (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - 3 figure collages on cloth; labeled #314-316, undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - 3 colored scrolls with a single mask on each one; labeled Nō Mask, Doolittle Collection #309-311, undated (Box 4)
  - 28 colored paintings of figures on tan fabric mounted on cardboard, undated; 9.5 inches x 10.75 inches (Box 5)
  - 3 colored paintings of landscape on tan fabric mounted on cardboard, undated; 9.5 inches x 10.75 inches (Box 5)
  - 1 colored painting of a bird on tan fabric mounted on cardboard, undated; 9.5 inches x 10.75 inches (Box 5)
  - 1 sketchbook containing 5 pencil drawings of costumes, 1934 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - 1 sketchbook of 4 pencil drawings of costumes, 1934 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - 1 sketchbook labeled "No-Dance I" and containing 34 pencil drawings of costumes and colored photographs and postcards of costumed actors, 1934 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Typed out: "Synopses of I. Ashi-Kari (The Reed Cutter). II. Yugyo-Yanagi (Preaching and the Willow). III. Ama (Fisher Girl). Kyogen, Fusenai (Already translated), and Nagamitsu (long and shining – Name of Sword)." "No Dramas. Complete Plays of Yuya. Dojoji. Synopsis of Kiyotsune, Farce Shuron, Tomonaga, Senjul Kurama Tengu-No plays.", undated (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - 1 scrapbook containing paste prints, photographs, and articles, undated (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - 1 accordion-style book with 5 colored paintings; labeled #242-246, undated (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - 1 accordion-style book entitled "No-Dance" with 61 colored prints of costumed Noh actors; labeled #247-307, undated (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - 1 pamphlet containing Chinese text; mask on cover, undated; 5 inches x 9 inches (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - 3 pamphlets; 3 prints; miscellaneous ephemera [folder labeled "Contents of this folder NOT Doolittle. From Baker Collection."], undated (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - 3 bound volumes containing colored paintings of figures and shop signs. English index indicates: "Dresses of the Tang, Sung, Yuan, Ming, Ch'ing Dynasty" and "Trade and Shop Signs;" labeled #317-354, undated (Box 8, Folder 1-3)
  - 1 portfolio "Murals in the Tomb of Li Chung-Jun of the Tang Dynasty" in English, French, and Chinese. Contains diagram of tomb and photographs of tomb wall drawings., 1974 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - 6 scrolls of varying sizes; both color and black and white illustrations; many inscribed, including: 1 scroll labeled, Nō Mask, Doolittle Collection #308; 2 scrolls containing signatures, including Mary Florence Denton, 1920 undated (Box 9)
  - 3 scrolls with color illustrations: 1 scene with 2 figures; 2 Nō Masks, labeled Doolittle Collection #312-313, undated (Box 10)